hi I'm bre andus and I wanted to take a
minute to talk about Squat and deadlift
form um now I could talk for an entire
hour about squats and deadlifts and the
different types and bar positions and
you know different types of loading um
but I'm just going to make this try to
make this quick and address some common
problems I'm seeing all over the place
with squats and deas so um problem
number
one uh anterior weight shift people are
trying to shift forward they don't want
to put their weight forward to make it a
quad dominant they don't know how to
kind of blend blend it to make it more
posterior chain so and that's because
they have weak glutes um weak glutes
weak hamstrings weak low back and and
spinal Erectors so it and it also
depends on the type of squat so if
you're squatting the parallel you want
to sit back you want to go like that
okay but if you're going doing a full
squat you're going all the way down this
I find most people do better by flaring
the toes slightly and letting their
knees kind of track out this way more
instead of their knees going straight
ahead and then it allows them to stay
more upright and
then just like this so if you notice in
a full squat I don't sit back I sit down
so here's a full squat okay I'm sitting
down but keep your chest up so that
brings me to another problem most people
can't full squat they can't go down to
this bottom position see how I'm
wiggling my toes I keep my chest up all
right most people if you ask them to get
in this position they're up under their
toes they're leaning over like this um
and this could be due to several reasons
but you need good ankle dorsy flexion
you need good hip flexion and you need
good thoracic extension just to be able
to sit in this position you also need
you know strong muscles and especially
strong stabilizers good glute Activation
so um you need to if if you can't get
into that position you need to be able
to get into that position so you got to
kind of pinpoint is it your is it your
ankle dors flexion is it your hip
flexion is it your thoracic extension is
it your glute activation you know are
you just weak from that position you
need to practice it more often and you
know develop some motor control so um
it's you it's imperative if you're going
to be a lifelong squatter you need to be
able to get in that position especially
if you're going to load it now um some
more common types of problems I see with
a squat is Val gets collapse okay people
want to squat down and their knees cave
in like this okay that's called Val get
collapse it's an adduction and internal
rotation of the hips while they squat so
that's usually due to Upper glute
strength glute medius and upper glute
Max fibers so you uh you want to
strengthen those and there's different
things you can do for example
um you
can
use a mini band and just
put it
around put it around your your legs like
this and kind of learn how to squat like
that okay that's one strategy but it all
mainly just takes practice keep your
knees out and don't let them cave in
eventually it becomes ingrained into
your motor patterns it becomes a motor
engram and it becomes automatic for you
um one thing I like to do um while
people are kind of learning how to squat
is I will use the Box they can't go deep
right now and do a full squat so I'll be
working on trying to get them deeper but
I'll still provide a training effect a
lot of times I'll put a weight in the
Goblet position like this and just have
them sit to a box
so I really like the box squat for
teaching the teaching the squat teaching
how to sit back and engage the posterior
chain okay um another problem people
will come down and SP and they come up
on their toes they don't push through
your heels we say push through your
heels we say a lot of things but it's
always a balance you don't want to be
like up onto your heels when you like
this you want to be pushing through your
whole foot but when you tell people push
through their heels they try to and it
ends up balancing out just like we tell
people sit back but if you're doing a
full squat you don't want to sit back
like this cuz you end up bending forward
too much like that so it depends on the
squat but in General people need to
learn how to sit back more um all right
uh and then you know the last thing
would be um people having especially
when they load it they have too much
forward bend so you'll watch people
squat now your forward bend your forward
trunk angle has a lot to do with where
you put the bar and also the type of
squat but in general if you do a high
bar s like this you are going to stay
more upright
because the bar stays balanced over your
feet so you're going to stay more
upright if you have the bar in the low
bar position now you're going to lean
forward a little bit more but it has to
do with anthropometry how your body
segment length your torso your tibia
your femur but it also has to do with um
your strength so I watch some people
they load it up and they'll go like
this and they'll lean forward so much
like that okay
people there's could be several reasons
why that's happening why people Bend
forward too much but sometimes it's how
they set up their feet a lot of people
are trying to go like this and then this
makes them lean too much so if they tap
or flare their feet out a bit and let
their knees track over their feet they
can go a little bit deeper now you also
need a lot of upper back strength to be
able to hold that the thoracic extensors
need to be really strong so again
practice practice practice front squats
in general are really good to do front
squats because it strengthens your upper
back and lets you stay more upright so
um um do front squats do box squats do
squats with a band around your knees
practice your form over and over and you
can become a good squatter so it's
really um just you know perfect practice
makes perfect you to keep trying keep
and it's got to look right if it if you
look in the mirror and your squat
doesn't look right then you know
something's wrong if it doesn't look
athletic something's wrong so you got to
make sure it looks athletic um keep
working on your mobility and stability
keep working on your form and eventually
it be you almost everyone can become
good squatters with practice there are
some people who just aren't built to
squat and we say you aren't built a
squat what does that mean all right a
lot of what your squat looks like has to
do with the length of your tibia femur
and your torso length so some people who
have really long Femur for example and
they go to squat they have to sit back a
lot they're going to lean more because
of their long femur so it's kind of like
a lightning bolt everyone is a lightning
bolt and how your lightning bolt looks
cuz the bar always stays centered over
the feet and you know the bar stay
Center over the feet so how you come
down and kind of collapse downwards like
an accordion that's how your squat looks
like so some people no matter you know
kind of like outliers of unique
anthropometries they're some of them are
never going to look good with a squat
but they can always box squat I've never
found someone who I can't get their box
squat to look good so box squat is good
it lets you use proper depth each time
you go down the same spot every time um
and you can load the weight in front
which helps you stay more upright so
that's why I love the box squat so
anyway I hope you found this video
useful just keep trying keep
strengthening the right parts make sure
you have good mobility and eventually
you will become a good squatter